<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Protestant Cemetery 2007</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p><!-- supply publication information-->
        </p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p><!-- supply information about the source --></p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div/>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart/>
        </docTitle>
      </titlePage>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div>
	<head>Cemetery data handling</head>
	<p>There is a great deal of data available to the project,
	from a set of disparate sources, shown
	schematically here:
	<graphic width="5in" url="pc2007.png"/></p>
	
	<list>
	  <item>The archaeological survey of monuments and graves carried out
	  in the 1980s, updated in 1996 and again in 2002. This records
	  each of the monuments in categorized  terms (ie by a taxonomy of
	  monument types, decorations, lettering methods, condition of
	  monument etc), as text (ie the
	  complete text of all inscriptions), and as prosopography (a summary
	  of the personal data contained in the inscriptions). This is
	  complemented by a digitized version of the cemetery outline plan.
	  The data items from this collection are shaded green on the schema
	  above. Identification of items is through an arbitary number
	  managed by the outline plan.</item>
	  <item>The cemetery's administrative record of burials and monuments
	  (shaded in blue on the schema), primarily related to
	  locations within the cemetery bounds. Graves and their
	  monuments are located by row position with an area.</item>
	  <item>The records of successive series of partial conservation
	  exercises, starting in the early 1980s and culminating in the present
	  project (shaded yellow on the schema).</item>
	  <item>Photographic records, most notably those of the Biblioteca
	  Herziana.</item>
	  <item>The immense amount of biographical information
	  generally available about the people buried in the cemetery.</item>
	</list>
	
	<p>The major problem with all the data records is that there
	is no unified way to refer to an object in the cemetery. There
	is no one-to-one relationship between a burial (the act of digging
	a hole and putting in the coffin of a named person), the erection
	of a monument (perhaps consisting of several parts, changing
	or being added to over time), and the prosopographic existence
	of the person commemorated on a monument. This is primarily because
	the cemetery no longer offers a permanent resting place, but
	re-uses the graves in the majority of the area. Monuments can be moved
	amalgamated, and changed (ie new inscriptions added)
	and graves can be extended or closed. The result is that we
	have allocated an important phase in the project to data
	management and integration.</p>
	
      </div>
      
      <div>
	<head>Project workpackages</head>

	<p><graphic width="5in" url="pc2007-plan.jpg"/></p>

	<div>
	  <head>System Design</head>
	  <p>Before any other work is started, the initial priority is
	  to establish the parameters of the project; both in terms of
	  which data sources are to be amalgamated to form a single
	  new database, and in terms of which outputs are to be
	  generated. At the least, the new system will be supporting:
	  <list type="ordered">
	  <item> the detailed scholarly record of the monuments and their
	  condition;</item>
	  <item> the administrative functions of the cemetery; and </item>
	  <item>a public-facing search and contribution site based mainly on
	  personal names.</item>
	  </list>
	  For all of these purposes, modelling of 
	  time and spatial dimensions is essential.</p>

	  <p>The archaeological records are currently held in an
	  archival format of XML files against a customization of the
	  Text Encoding Initiative (<ptr
	  target="http://www.tei-c.org/"/>), including polygon data
	  making up the outline plan.</p>

	  <p>The target system will deliver XML data via web services 
	  for both textual and geolocating data, to offer maximum
	  flexibility for public and internal querying, update and
	  annotation. Several different web-based interfaces will be
	  created for use by the different stakeholders, but this is
	  not specified within the scope of the current project.</p>

	  <p>The new system will be set up so that new monuments added
	  to the cemetery will be included as they put in place,
	  rather than waiting for future surveys.</p>

	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Sebastian Rahtz</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>dataflow diagrams covering all cemetery
	    material</item>
	    <item>comprehensive scheme for object
	    identification</item>
	    <item>specification of web-based systems</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Database alignment</head>
	  <p>After agreement on the overall design, existing data
	  sources need to be examined to find the points of
	  intersection. This will form the basis of creating a unified
	  database by setting the rules by which records will be
	  considered to point the same object. The system will have
	  two primary identifiers, a grid-based location of objects
	  (both monuments and burials), and an absolute numbering
	  system for monumental groups.</p>

	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Sebastian Rahtz</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>implementation of identification scheme</item>
	    <item>migration procedures specification</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>
	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Database merging</head>
	  <p>The target of this work package is to complete
	  the record alignment process in all databases, and transfer
	  the information to a common system.	  </p>
	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Sebastian Rahtz</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>internal consistent database containing all information</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>
	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Additional surveying</head>
	  <p>The current cemetery plan is essentially schematic, rather than
	  giving a detailed survey of each grave, and defines a
	  set of coordinates outlining each monument. This example
	  shows the detail provided:</p>
	  <p><graphic width="5in" url="plansample.jpg"/></p>
	  <p>This work package will bring the plan up to date, by
	  locating new graves within the same system, and aligning the
	  arbitrary cemetery grid with absolute coordinates. The plan
	  will then continue to be maintained as a polygon associated
	  with  each monument group.</p>
	  <p>This work package will produce a report on the
	  feasibility of a new survey of the cemetery in the
	  future.</p>

	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Nicholas Stanley-Price</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>digital plan in DXF or SVG format, 
	    correlated with latitude/longitude</item>
	    <item>feasibility report on new survey</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	</div>

	<div>
	  <head>Identificatory photography</head>
	  <p>Although many of the more dramatic or important monuments
	  have been photographed many times, there is no formal record
	  of each monument, and most of the existing photographs have
	  not been digitized. This workpackage will deliver at least
	  one digital photograph of each monument, and will produce a
	  report on the feasibility of digitizing the existing
	  photographic collection.</p>
	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Christine Payling</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>at least one digital image for each monument, tied
	    to database</item>
	    <item>feasibility report on digitizing older photographs</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	</div>

	<div>
	  <head>Conservation survey</head>
	  <p>One of the main aims of this project is to assess the
	  work needed to bring the stone monuments in the cemetery
	  into a state where ongoing planned maintenance is
	  sustainable. This requires a preliminary re-assessment of
	  all stones and their location (the presence of many trees in
	  the cemetery is a considerable issue), and correlating this
	  with the archaeological data (material, size etc) to draw up
	  a scheme of work.</p>
	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Nicholas Stanley-Price</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>consistent summary report on all monuments</item>
	    <item>detailed recommendations for full conservation exercise</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Monument record checking</head>
	  <p>This workpackage will check the archaeological survey of
	  the 1980s. Each record will be checked against the stone,
	  and enhanced where needed; this will particularly apply to 
	  aspects of the record which may affect conservation work, eg
	  material type, lettering type, and monument type.</p>
	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Christine Payling</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>each monument visited at least once and record
	    checked</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>


	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Monument record adding</head>
	  <p>Some 500-600 monuments added to the cemetery in the last
	  20 years have been surveyed, but not yet
	  digitized or merged into the main record. This workpackage
	  involves digitizing these records, and checking for 
	  monuments added since 2002.</p>
	  <p><hi>Task leader:</hi> Sebastian Rahtz</p>
	  <p><hi>Task deliverables:</hi>
	  <list>
	    <item>all monuments and graves added since 1996 added to
	    database to same standard as 1984 survey</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	</div>
      </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
